Elisha Hunt Allen Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Elisha Hunt Allen Papers 1849-1934 (bulk 1867-1882)
MSS10447
Allen, Elisha Hunt, 1804-1883
2,000 items
6 containers plus 1 oversize
3 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Diplomat, jurist, lawyer, and United States representative from Maine. Correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, photographs, printed matter, and miscellaneous material largely concerning Hawaiian economic and political conditions, sugar plantations and trade, Chinese labor, the Hawaiian supreme court, of which Allen was chief justice, and the United States-Hawaiian Reciprocity Treaty of 1876.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allen family--Correspondence.; Allen, Elisha Hunt, 1804-1883.; Allen, Mary Hobbs, 1829-1880--Correspondence.; Bishop, Charles Reed, 1822-1915--Correspondence.; Green, William Lowthian, 1819-1890--Correspondence.; Harris, Charles Coffin, 1822-1881--Correspondence.; Kalakaua, David, King of Hawaii, 1836-1891--Correspondence.; Severance, Henry W., 1828-1908--Correspondence.; Welch, Andrew, Sr., approximately 1838-1889--Correspondence.
Organizations
Hawaii. Supreme Court.
Subjects
Chinese--Hawaii.; Courts--Hawaii.; Labor--Hawaii.; Plantations--Hawaii.; Reciprocity (Commerce)--Hawaii.; Reciprocity (Commerce)--United States.; Sugar trade--Hawaii.; Working class--Hawaii.
Places
Hawaii--Commerce--United States.; Hawaii--Economic conditions.; Hawaii--Foreign relations--United States.; Hawaii--Politics and government--To 1893.; Maine--Politics and government.; United States--Commerce--Hawaii.; United States--Foreign relations--Hawaii.; United States--Foreign relations--Treaties.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Judges.; Justices, State--Hawaii.; Lawyers.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Maine.
Provenance
The papers of Elisha Hunt Allen, diplomat, jurist, lawyer, and United States representative from Maine, were given to the Library of Congress by Mary Jane Allen and Frederick Allen in 1935.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Elisha Hunt Allen are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1804, Jan. 28 Born, New Salem, Mass.
1823 Graduated Williams College, Williamstown, Mass.
1826 Admitted to Massachusetts bar
1828 Married Sarah Elizabeth Fessenden (died 1845)
1835 1840 Member, Maine House of Representatives
1841 1843 Member, United States House of Representatives from Maine
1849 Member, Massachusetts House of Representatives
1850 1853 United States consul to Hawaii
1853 1857 Minister of finance, Kingdom of Hawaii
1857 Married Mary Harrod Hobbs
1857 1877 Chancellor and Chief Justice of the Kingdom of Hawaii Supreme Court
1876 Negotiated the United States-Hawaii Reciprocity Treaty
1876 1883 United States minister to Hawaii
1883, Jan. 1 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Elisha Hunt Allen (1804-1883) span the years 1849-1934, with the bulk of the material dating from 1867 to 1882. The papers consist of correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, awards and diplomas, invitations, passports, photographs, statistical tables, printed matter, and miscellaneous items and are organized into the following series: Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Hawaiian Legation Correspondence, Subject File, Miscellany, and Oversize.
The Family Correspondence contains letters from Allen to his second wife, Mary Hobbs Allen, and a few letters to other members of the Allen family. Correspondents in the General Correspondence include Charles Reed Bishop, W. L. Green, Charles Coffin Harris, Henry W. Severance, and Andrew Welch. The Hawaiian Legation Correspondence contains drafts and a letterbook of official letters sent from the Hawaiian Legation. Subjects of interest covered in the several correspondence series as well as in the Subject File and Miscellany include the United States-Hawaiian Reciprocity Treaty of 1876, the Hawaiian supreme court, sugar plantations and trade, Chinese labor, and Hawaiian economic and political conditions from 1850 to 1882.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Family Correspondence, 1849-1934
General Correspondence, 1857-1882
Hawaiian Legation Correspondence, 1877-1883
Subject File, 1853-1882
Miscellany, 1867-1883
Oversize, 1867-1880
Container List
- Family Correspondence, 1849-1934 (Box 1-2)
  Letters from Allen to family members including his second wife, Mary Hobbs Allen.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member.
  - Allen, Elisha H., Jr., 1877-1882 (Box 1)
  - Allen, Mary Hobbs (Box 1)
    - 1849-1871, (7 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1872-1880, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Allen, William F., 1867-1882 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1861-1934 (Box 2)
- General Correspondence, 1857-1882 (Box 3-4)
  Correspondence and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Bishop, Charles Reed., 1869-1880 (Box 3)
  - Carter, H. A. P., 1875-1882 (Box 3)
  - Cheng Tsao Ju, 1882 (Box 3)
  - Frelinghuysen, Frederick T., 1882 (Box 3)
  - Gibson, Walter Murray, 1879-1882 (Box 3)
  - Green, W. L., 1874-1881 (Box 3)
  - Harris, Charles Coffin, 1857-1881 (Box 3)
  - Hitt, Robert R., 1881 (Box 3)
  - Kalakaua, David, King of Hawaii, 1876-1882 (Box 3)
  - Severance, Henry W., 1878-1882 (Box 3)
  - Smith, J. Mott, 1869-1882 (Box 3)
  - Welch, Andrew, 1875-1882 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Y, 1867-1882 (Box 4)
- Hawaiian Legation Correspondence, 1877-1883 (Box 4)
  Letters sent and received and letterbook.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Letters received on death of Allen, 1883 (Box 4)
  - Letters sent, drafts, 1877-1882 (Box 4)
  - Letterbook, 1877-1879 (Box 4)
- Subject File, 1853-1882 (Box 5)
  Treaties, trade records, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Trade, 1857-1882 (Box 5)
  - Treaties, miscellaneous, 1853-1880 (Box 5)
  - Treaty, U.S.-Hawaii, 1855-1882 (Box 5)
- Miscellany, 1867-1883 (Box 6)
  Invitations, passports, photographs, speeches and writings, statistical tables, and printed matter.
  - Biographical material (Box 6)
  - Commissions, statistical tables, and letters of credence, 1867, 1874-1880 See Oversize (Box 6)
  - Invitations (Box 6)
  - Obituaries, 1883 (Box 6)
  - Passports (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Speeches and other writings (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Printed matter (Box 6)
    - Allen family (Box 6)
    - Hawaii (Box 6)
    - Portrait of Allen (Box 6)
    - Hawaiian royal family (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Oversize, 1867-1880 (Box OV 1)
  Commissions, statistical tables, and letters of credence
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Commissions, statistical tables, and letters of credence, 1867, 1874-1880 (Container 6) (Box OV 1)